Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Caricatures and Cartoons 1643, 1756-1943, 1977 PR 10
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society collection of caricatures and cartoons
1643, 1756-1943, 1977
New-York Historical Society
PR 10
56 Linear feet in 155 flat file folders and 2 flat boxes (approximately 1600 items)
The collection holds about 1600 prints (mostly engravings and lithographs) and pen and ink drawings of humorous and caustic pictorial commentary on political events and social customs. The caricatures range from the late colonial period in British North America to the mid-twentieth century, with just a few outliers from before and after that range. The bulk of the collection, with about 1300 items, dates from the Jacksonian era beginning in 1828 to the close of the 19th century. Political matters are especially well-represented in the collection, especially in connection with the electoral politics of Presidential campaigns. Economic policies (e.g., banking, currency, financial speculation, tariff reform, growth of industrial power, etc.) is a major theme. African-Americans appear frequently in the images, either as principal subjects or in the background as a subtext to the often layered caricatures of the 19th century. Slavery, abolition and the perceived ability (or inability) of emancipated African-Americans to participate as equals in American society are common subjects in this regard. Other subjects that run through the collection are political corruption (especially in relation to Tammany), America's relation with the rest of the world, social issues, and America at war.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 7 chronological series:
Series I. Colonial & Revolutionary Period, 1643, 1756-1790
Series II. Early Republic Period, 1792-1826
Series III. Jacksonian Period, 1828-1840
Series IV. Antebellum Period, 1841-1859
Series V. Civil War and Post-War Period, 1860-1868
Series VI. Late 19th Century, 1869-1899
Series VII. Undetermined Dates, 19th century-20th century
Within each series, the caricatures are arranged in approximate chronological order, using a unique identifier assigned at some point in the past by N-YHS (see processing note). For those without a previously-assigned identifier, just the year and "No #" was used.
Conditions Governing Access
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was compiled by New-York Historical Society from various gifts and purchases. When the collection was inventoried in 2019-2022 for this finding aid, any acquisition information noted on the document itself was included in the item level note here. Additional information from the accession ledgers may be added over time.
Scope and Contents
The collection holds about 1600 prints (mostly engravings and lithographs) and pen and ink drawings of humorous and caustic pictorial commentary on political events and social customs. The publication of single-sheet caricatures blossomed in the mid-1700s, and such individually issued prints comprise the bulk of the collection, which also include drawings for editorial cartoons published in newspapers. The caricatures range from the late colonial period in British North America to the mid-twentieth century, with just a few outliers from before and after that range. The bulk of the collection, with about 1300 items, dates from the Jacksonian era beginning in 1828 to the close of the 19th century.
Political matters are especially well-represented in the collection, especially in connection with the electoral politics of Presidential campaigns. Economic policies (e.g., banking, currency, financial speculation, tariff reform, growth of industrial power, etc.) is a major theme, both within the context of presidential elections and as a general theme in the development of the nation. Political corruption is often caricatured, and New York City's Democratic Party (referred to commonly as Tammany, after its headquarters, Tammany Hall) is often the chief target.
African-Americans appear frequently in the images, either as principal subjects or in the background as a subtext to the often layered caricatures of the 19th century. Slavery, abolition and the perceived ability (or inability) of emancipated African-Americans to participate as equals in American society are common subjects in this regard, and commonly drawn with racist imagery, such as in the 1828 "Life in Philadelphia" series and the "Darktown" series of the 1880s drawn by Thomas Worth, James Cameron, and others and published by Currier & Ives.
Over 200 items trace the Civil War era, through the 1860 election and 1864 re-election of Abraham Lincoln, the secession crisis of 1861, the Emancipation Proclamation of 1863, and the battles through to the close of the war. The Spanish-American War is also well-represented with about 270 caricatures from Puck, The Judge, The Bee, The Verdict, and other publications. The disputes between Britain and America and the resulting War for Independence, and then the War of 1812, are represented with many caricatures. The Mexican War, World War I, and World War II have lesser representation.
America's relation with the rest of the world is a common theme. Early on, through the Civil War, these seem to focus principally on concerns with how the European powers (including Russia) perceive the United States and how the new nation might be undermined. Post-Civil War, the theme seems to shift with the United States greater standing in relation to Europe, with an increased paternalism toward Asia and the Caribbean.
Social caricatures can also be found in the collection, often related to the changing role of women, the expanding wealth of the country, class tensions, and the like. Major national events, such as the Gold Rush, are the subject of several caricatures.
Major artists and publishers of lithographed cartoons represented in the collection include, among others, James Baillie, Edward W. Clay, Currier & Ives, David Claypoole Johnston, Thomas Nast, Henry R. Robinson, and Thomas W. Strong. Among the original pen and ink drawings are approximately 35 by Thomas Nast, the chief American cartoonist of the 1870s and 80s.
The finding aid lists most of the caricatures in the collection individually. Titles were transcribed from catalog cards, supplemented with visual confirmation. Additional or clarifying subject headings noted by the archivists are included in [brackets]. Certain "sets" of caricatures, such as the 270 works concerning the Spanish-American War, were listed in more summary fashion.
Some items were not found in the collection during the inventory of 2019-22 although they did have a card catalog record. Generally, these items were listed in this inventory based on the catalog description and noted here as missing.
Separated Materials
Three sets of caricatures, formerly in the collection, were removed and cataloged separately:
* "Album californiano [picture]: colleción de tipos" (call phrase Print Room Rare F865.F37 1850 Oversize)
* Homer Davenport drawings (PR 125)
* King Features Syndicate drawings (PR 446)
Related Materials
The Subject File collection (PR 68) also holds prints that overlap to some degree with the subject content of the caricature collection. See especially the U.S. History folders in that collection.
African Americans.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Political corruption -- New York (State) -- New York.; Presidents -- United States -- Election.; Spanish-American War, 1898; Tariff -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- Politics and government.; Caricatures.; Editorial cartoons.; Engravings (prints); Drawings (visual works); Lithographs.; Baillie, James S., active 1838-1855; Clay, Edward Williams, 1799-1857; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Keppler, Joseph Ferdinand, 1838-1894.; Keppler, Udo J., 1872-1956; Kirby, Rollin, 1875-1952; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Magee, John L.; McClellan, George B. (George Brinton), 1826-1885; Nast, Thomas, 1840-1902; Robinson, Henry R., -1850; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Zimmerman, Eugene, 1862-1935; Currier & Ives; Tammany Hall (Political organization)
- Series I. Colonial & Revolutionary Period, 1643, 1756-1790
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes prints dating from 1756 to 1790 (with one earlier print from 1643), that is, from the late colonial period in British North America and the beginning of the American Revolution to the close of the Revolution and beginning of American government under the new Constitution of 1787. There are about 140 prints in the series, 50 of which are a set of British political satires dating from 1756-1757. Though most of the series relates to America and the Revolutionary period, the focus of the series does have an international perspective with British, French, and Dutch themes. Many of the prints are in, or include, the French, Dutch, and German languages.
  The container list includes "BM" (for British Museum) numbers for many of the prints. This refers to numbers in the "Catalogue of Prints and Drawings in the British Museum, [Volume 4], Division I, Political and Personal Satires " and can assist in finding further data and images about the item on the internet.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in approximate chronological order.
  - Let Not The World Divide Those Whom Christ Hath Joined, 1643 (Folder FF-1, Item 1643-1)
  - British Political Satire. 51 cards., 1756 (Box 1)
    51 cards, approximately 4 1/2 x 3 1/2 inches, mostly by Edwards & Darly from 1756. At least one from 1757. Several undated and/or unattributed. N-YHS's records refer to these as the "Townsend cards," possibly because of their source.
    All are described in the "Catalogue of Prints and Drawings in the British Museum, [Volume 4], Division I, Political and Personal Satires" (available in Google Books). The catalogue numbers held are: 3344, 3346,3348, 3356, 3362, 3381, 3385, 3388, 3390, 3392, 3394, 3399, 3401, 3403, 3407, 3412, 3414, 3417, 3424, 3427, 3429, 3442, 3473, 3488, 3490, 3493, 3495, 3497, 3499, 3502, 3504 (colored), 3506 (colored), 3511, 3516, 3518, 3521, 3522 (colored), 3527, 3531, 3533, 3535 (colored), 3537, 3542, 3543, 3558, 3564, 3572, 3576, 3578, 3602, 3638.
  - The English Lioned Dismember'd [Loss of Minorca; French-Indian War], 1756 (Folder FF-1, Item 1756-1)
  - The Germans bleeds & bears ye Furs of Quaker Lords & Savage Curs..., 1764 (Folder FF-1, Item 1764-1)
    Removed from pamphlet. Y1764.Paxton. Engraving - Henry Dawkins
  - The Deplorable State of America or Sc---h Government [Scotch Government; Stamp Act], 1765 (Folder FF-1, Item 1765-1)
    BM #4119; Attributed by Murrell to Wilkinson. Acquisition date: Oct 7, 1901.
  - The Great Financier or British OEconomy for the Years 1763, 1764, 1765 [Stamp Act] (Folder FF-1, Item 1765-2)
    BM #4128 (variation). Acquisition date: July 16, 1908?
  - The Repeal. Or The Funeral of Miss Ame - Stamp [Stamp Act Repeal], 1766 (Folder FF-2, Item 1766-1)
    BM #4140 (variant); There is a second variation of the caricature. Second variation has note re: acquisition?: Adlard(?) Feb/61. There is a third variation (a facsimile).
  - The Colonies Reduced. Its Companion., 1768 (Folder FF-2, Item 1768-1)
    BM #4183; Designed & Engraved for The Political Register, London. Catalogue Note states that it is probably by Benjamin Franklin.
  - Magna Britania her Colonies Reduc'd, 1768 (Folder FF-2, Item 1768-2)
    For the Political Register; Probably designed by Benjamin Franklin; Gift of Miss Annie Dennis, Oct. 17, 1933.
  - No Title [Four Lines of Verse - Avaunt Ye Troublers of a World's Repose...], 1768 (Folder FF-2, Item 1768-3)
    2 copies; from London Magazine, Vol. XXXVII, frontispiece.
  - Janus 1768-1769 (Folder FF-2, Item 1768-4)
    BM # 4233; Designed & Engraved for the Political Register
  - The Pillars of the State, 1768 (Folder FF-2, Item 1768-5)
    BM #4235; Designed & Engraved for the Political Register
  - The City Carriers., 1769 (Folder FF-2, Item 1769-1)
    BM #4296; From London Magazine
  - Privy Purse in 1753. Privy Purse in 1773.The Mother and The Child (Folder FF-3, Item 1773-1)
    BM #5105; For the London Magazine, p. 33
  - The Parricide. A Sketch of Modern Patriotism., 1773 (Folder FF-3, Item 1773-2)
    BM #5334; Engraved for the Westminster Magazine (* published 1773-1785)
  - A New Method of Macarony Making, As Practiced at Boston [Two Stanzas of verse follow. The Boston Port Bill], 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-1)
    BM #5232; Printed for Carington Bowles; There is a reissue (1774-1R) of the original drawing published by H.R. Robinson between 1837-1842.(Reissue has an acquisition (?) date on front of May 29, 1904.)
  - The Bostonian's Paying the Excise-man, or Tarring & Feathering. [Boston Port Bill], 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-2)
    Printed for Robert Sayer & J. Bennett. On back states "Property of The Naval History Society...Dec. 8, 1932. Gift of James Barnes and John Sanford Barnes."; There is a reissue (1774-2R) of the original drawing published by H.R. Robinson between 1837 and 1842. On the front of the reissued caricature is the acquisition(?) date May 29, 1904.
  - The Bostonians in Distress [Boston Port Bill], 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-3)
    BM #5241; Printed for R. Sayer & J. Bennett. Noted as gift of the Naval History Society, Dec 8, 1932.
  - Liberty Triumphant. or the Downfall of Oppression. [Independence of America], 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-4)
    Front has acquisition(?)date - Apr 16, 1906.
  - The Able Doctor. or America Swallowing the Bitter Draught, 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-5)
    BM #5226; From the London Magazine, July 1774; Copied by Paul Revere for the Royal American Magazine, 1774
  - The Mitred Minuet, 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-6)
    BM #5228; From the London Magazine, 1774, p. 312
  - The Council of the Rulers and Elders against the Tribe of Ye Americanites, 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-7)
    BM #5281
  - America in Flames, 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-8)
    BM #5282; From Town and Country Magazine, 1774, p.659
  - The Polish Plumb Cake, 1774 (Folder FF-3, Item 1774-9)
    BM #5229; J. Lodge, sculptor. From the Westminster Magazine
  - The Patriotick Barber of New York [Boston Port Bill], 1775 (Folder FF-5, Item 1775-1)
    BM #5284; Printed for R. Sayer & J. Bennett.
  - The Political Cartoon of the Year, 1775 (Folder FF-4, Item 1775-2)
    BM #5288; for the Westminster Magazine
  - The Thistle Reel, 1775 (Folder FF-4, Item 1775-3)
    BM #5285; For the London Magazine, 1775,p.56
  - The Court Cotillion, Or the Premiers new Parl*****t Jig, 1775 (Folder FF-4, Item 1775-4)
    BM #5244; Terry del et Sculp.
  - Billiard Playing in 1776. Local Option or Not, We'll Play Billiards (Folder FF-6, Item 1776-1)
    Published by John Leopold, from an original painting. Note on back: "Trade Card for Billiard Table Mfr. Bella C. Landauer Coll. Filed Sports and Games"
  - News from America, or The Patriots in the Dumps, 1776 (Folder FF-6, Item 1776-2)
    BM #5340; For the London Magazine, Nov. 1776
  - Miss Carolina Sullivan, one of the obstinate daughters of America 1776 [Moultrie's successful repulse of Sir Peter Parker's fleet off Charleston] (Folder FF-6, Item 1776-3)
    Signed Matting D1 Del. Published by Mary Darly
  - Cupid's Tower, 1776 (Folder FF-6, Item 1776-4a)
    BM #5377; published by M. Darly
  - Bunkers Hill or American Head Dress, 1776 (Folder FF-6, Item 1776-4b)
    BM #5330 (variant); published by M. Darly
  - Oh-Heigh-Oh or a View of the Back Settlements, 1776 (Folder FF-6, Item 1776-5)
    Published by M Darly
  - Die Generals und Officiers der Koniglich Englischen Armee und derer Hutffs Truppen zu Neu Yorck [Title also in French], 1776 (Folder FF-6, Item 1776-6)
    Grave par Jean Borait Winckler. Froost pinxit; Printed for Carington Bowles
  - A Picturesque View of the State of the Nation for February 1778 [British Commerce] (Folder FF-7, Item 1778-1)
    BM #5472; One of four variants; Acquisition(?) Date on back: Feb 26, 1900
  - Explication de ce tableau touchant l'etat de la Nation d'Angleterre [Title also in German], 1778 (Folder FF-7, Item 1778-2)
    Second variant of A Picturesque View of the State...; on back are designs for Clothes Press & Cedar Trunks for A. Henderson Carpenter
  - No Title [Variant of A Picturesque View ...], 1778 (Folder FF-7, Item 1778-3)
    Third variant of A Picturesque View of the State ...
  - Evil to him who turns to Evil says Poor Richard [Title in French], 1778 (Folder FF-7, Item 1778-4)
    Fourth variant of A Picturesque View of the State... Acquisition(?) date on front of April 22, 1905.
  - Poor Old England! or 1778. or the Bl-s-d Effects of a Wise Administration (Folder FF-7, Item 1778-5)
    A hand-colored variant of A Picturesque View of the State...; Printed for W.M. Jackson.
  - The Commissioners., 1778 (Folder FF-8, Item 1778-6)
    BM #5473; signed M Darly, published M. Darly; acquisition date on back: Mar. 27, 1957 (Abbott-Lenox Fund)
  - Dedicated to the English Admiralty by a member of the American Congress [Title in French; tobacco trade], 1778 (Folder FF-8, Item 1778-7)
    BM #5472 (variant); drawn from nature in Boston by Corbut; engraved in Philadelphia.
  - Dedicated to the English Admiralty by a member of the American Congress [Title in French; tobacco trade], 1778 (Folder FF-8, Item 1778-8)
    Variant of above; colored; Acquisition date on back: Nov. 15, 1938 Wilbur Fund
  - The Tea-Tax Tempest, or the Anglo American Revolution [2 copies - Title is in English, German, French], 1778 (Folder FF-8, Item 1778-9)
    BM #5490; second copy is proof before letters. Acquisition(?) date on back of second copy: December 31, 1953.
  - An Hieroglyphick Poetic Epistle [Rebus], 1778 (Folder FF-8, Item 1778-10)
    From Don Deigo of Spain to Louis Le Grand of France; Acquisition(?) date on front: July 16, 1908.
  - Britannia to America [Title in picture writing; Rebus], 1778 (Folder FF-8, Item 1778-11)
    BM #5474 (variant); published by M. Darly; Acquisition(?) date on back: Feb. 26, 1958.
  - America to her Mistaken Mother [Title in picture writing; Rebus], 1778 (Folder FF-8, Item 1778-12)
    BM #5475; published by M. Darly
  - The Political Raree Show: or a Picture of Parties and Politics, during and at the close of the Last Session of Parliament, June 1779. (Folder FF-9, Item 1779-1)
    BM #5548; Published by Fielding & Walker for the Westminster Magazine, June 1779; Acquisition(?) date on front: Feb [?] 1900.
  - Prattle [Military Operations], 1779 (Folder FF-9, Item 1779-2)
    BM #5603 (variant); published by M. Darly
  - The European Diligence [European Politics], 1779 (Folder FF-9, Item 1779-3)
    BM #5557; "sold by W. H___"; Acquisition(?) date on front: July 16, 1908.
  - The Man in the White Shirt, or Foolish False Pride. [Title in Dutch; The Defensive Alliance], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-1)
    BM # 5716A (variant). Dutch title: De man in 'thembd, of de gefnuikte hoogmoed." This is a proof from unfinished plate. Acquisition(?) date on front: June 21, 1906.
  - The Man in the White Shirt, or Foolish False Pride. [Title in Dutch; The Defensive Alliance], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-2)
    BM #5716; Dutch title: De man in 'thembd, of de gefnuikte hoogmoed." Completed version of plate above. Acquisition(?) date on front: June 21, 1906.
  - Through the Forceful Attack of the Lion [Title in Dutch], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-3)
    BM #5712; title in Dutch: "Den door list en geweld aangevallen leeuw." Acquisition(?) date on front: June 21, 1906.
  - The Desperate British and the Pleased Americans on Receiving the News of a Defensive Alliance, Unlimited Convoy, and Armed Neutrality [Title in Dutch; Dutch Resistance to Navigation Acts], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-4)
    BM #5724; title in Dutch: De wanhoopie britten, en de vernoegde americanen..." Acquisition date on back: April 16, 1906.
  - Verklaaring [Dutch; Dutch-American Commerce], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-5)
    BM #5729. Acquisition(?) date on front: June 21, 1906.
  - The British Leopard Brought to Reason [Title in Dutch; Navigation Acts], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-6 (marked 1780-7))
    BM #5719. Title in Dutch: Den Britsen Leopard tot Reden gebracht." Key to numbered figures not added; Acquisition(?) date on front: Feb. 26, 1900.
  - John Bull Triumphant, 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-7)
    BM #5624; Published by W. Humphrey; hand-colored engraving
  - No Title - Bold Jack [verse in both English & Dutch; Dutch propaganda for the U.S.], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-8)
    BM #5721/5721A (variant); 2 copies: Copy 1 with stone wall border; Copy 2 without stone wall border
  - Wages After Work [Title in Dutch; British Commerce], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-9)
    BM #5715. Title in Dutch: "Loon na werk." 2 copies; Copy 2 is from the Naval History Society Collection.
  - The Proud and the Watchful Lion [Title in Dutch], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-10)
    BM #5714. Title in Dutch: "De moedige en waakzaame leeuw."
  - Four Portraits in Caricature Titled (in French): Darby, Le Lord North, Le Lord Cornwall, Le Lord Rawdon, 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-11)
    BM #6048-6049
  - The Lion is Waking Up [Title in Dutch], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-12)
    BM #5713. Title in Dutch: "De ontwaakte leeuw." Stapled behind engraving is key [Dutch]. Acquisition(?) date on front: June 21, 1906.
  - Engelsch Nieuws [Dutch; Dutch-British Relations], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-13)
    BM #5722 (variant?)
  - No Title [Edwardigen Nederlander; Dutch Investments], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-14)
    BM #5720; print before letters
  - De Tyd Geeft Verandering. [Dutch], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-15)
    BM #5718
  - Dan Onder Dan Booven [Dutch], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-16)
    BM #5725
  - De Verloste Hollander, or De Gedwongen Dog [Dutch], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-17)
    BM #5732
  - Den Engelsman Op Zyn Uiterste [Dutch; also Title in French], 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-18)
    BM #5731; Published by Nicolas Ciseau
  - Algemeene Staatkundige Konstplaat Van't Jaar 1780. [Dutch] (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-19)
    BM #5728
  - Yankee Doodle, or The American Satan, 1780 (Folder FF-10, Item 1780-20)
    Penned inscription: "Joseph Wright, son of Patience Wright. Ask me not what provocation I have had that strong antipathy Good bears to Bad. Pub. by Ebenezer Scalpp'em on the banks of the Ohio."
  - The State Watchman Discovered by the Genius of Britain, studying plans for the Reduction of America. [George III and the American Revolution], 1781 (Folder FF-11, Item 1781-1)
    BM #5856; published by I. Jones. On back: "by Rowlandson, I. Jones published after the news of the Surrender at Yorktown.". Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 16, 1906.
  - The Ballance of Power [International Rivalry], 1781 (Folder FF-11, Item 1781-2)
    BM #5827; Engraving by RS; published by R. Wilkinson
  - A New Pantomine. Harlequine. [American independence], 1781 (Folder FF-11, Item 1781-3)
  - Liberty Enlightned, 1781 (Folder FF-11, Item 1781-4)
    BM #5833; Caricature describing the election of Henry Cruger, who later became elected to the New York State Senate after The War, as Mayor of Bristol, England. Acquisition(?) date on back - Jan. 27, 1960. NYT Fd.
  - No Title [variant of above, Liberty Enlightned], 1781 (Folder FF-11, Item 1781-5)
    BM #5833 (variant); On back - Jan 27, 1960, NYT Fd.
  - No Title [York Town], 1781 (Folder FF-11, Item 1781-6)